while you may already know this a
barbell can help take you to the next
level in the weight room because it can
handle all the different exercises that
you might throw at it but what can't a
barbell do well it can't clean itself so
today i'm going to take apart this
barbell and show you guys how to clean
it
what's up everybody it's jake back in
the barbing garage gym and i have a bit
of a different video for you guys today
i'm going to take apart this barbell and
show you how to properly clean it so it
stays in good shape for years to come
but before i get started with any of
that i have to let you know we've
reviewed a lot of barbells on barbin.com
and if you want to browse our best list
just google barbin best barbells and you
can decide for yourself which one suits
you the best now let's get to it all
right guys so before you get started on
cleaning your barbell there's some
supplies that you're gonna want to go
and get just to make sure you do it the
proper way so first and foremost i would
definitely recommend getting yourself a
pair of safety glasses because you can
never be too careful
you're gonna want to get some
three-in-one multi-purpose oil this is
going to be used to lubricate the
sleeves and make that spin happen which
you really want in a multi-purpose bar
such as this one right here now i have
seen people use wd-40 for that but i've
also read that that could actually
cause more dust and dirt to build up
within your sleeves and you really don't
want that
you're gonna want an old rag t-shirt
whatever it may be to wipe everything
off this is an old pair of sheets i cut
up it really doesn't matter and then i
would definitely recommend getting a
pair of gloves as well because i don't
know about you but i don't really want
all that oil all over my hands
so
within your loading sleeves you're going
to find a set of snap rings and washers
hold it together so you're definitely
going to want a pair of snap ring pliers
just to get those snap rings out of
there
you also might want a little
multi-purpose tool like this just
something thin you might not need it but
if something does get wedged and you
need a little bit more leverage this is
going to help you out
and when it comes to cleaning the
knurling you're going to want to get
yourself a nice nylon brush i do say
nylon because if you were to get
stainless steel
that could cause some scratches and
that's going to potentially lead to more
dust dirt dead skin buildup within your
bar which obviously is not what you're
looking for you're going to want a short
bristled brush this isn't as short as i
would like it to be but i still think
this is going to get the job done all
right so i'm gonna throw my goggles on
let's get to it
you're gonna want to put your hand over
top of the barbell just to make sure
that snap ring doesn't fly out on you
all right guys these clearly are not
working
and it's making my head hurt a little
bit so i'm tired of dealing with that
we're gonna head down to lowe's and get
us a solid pair of snap ring pliers so
come on follow me let's go
all right y'all we're here at lowe's now
we're gonna get us a good pair of snap
ring pliers make sure you get your
yourself a pair like these they just
seem so much better in my hands and
let's get back to it i'm excited
hey
double recording
let's get it
right here that's what we needed let's
go
all right guys we're finally back from
lowe's with that solid pair of snap ring
pliers that i desperately needed here
and first impressions right off the bat
they just feel better in my hands
overall and they feel sturdier and
like they're gonna do the trick way
better than these ever could so let's
put my goggles back on
and let's get to it once again you're
gonna want to put your hand over the end
of the barbell because you don't want
that snap ring to fly out which could
happen look at that that is so much
easier guys and this is a really good
thing to
also do make sure you don't lose
anything you're gonna have a set of snap
rings and washers within your sleeve and
it's important that they stay in the
same order so that when you put it back
together everything is properly where it
needs to be so i'm using a tissue you
can use paper towel paper plate really
whatever
this is just really important to do so
once you get that outer snap ring out
just simply hit your barbell your cap's
gonna fly out and
like i said we caused a lot of damage to
ours which
it's not gonna change the way the
barbell works but it might drive you
crazy if you get it scratched up like
this and that's definitely gonna drive
me crazy so let's get this inner snap
ring out now
okay guys this is ridiculous how much
easier this is
so once you get that inner snap ring out
just simply slide your sleeve back
you're gonna find
a washer and some barbells actually do
have a shim if you do have one like this
one that's gonna be right after your
washer
right after that is a pair of half moon
washers
so take both of those out
and once again make sure you keep
everything in the right order
and then as you slide it a little bit
more
there is another washer in the very back
all right so once you get that last
washer out of there definitely go and
put your gloves on like i already have
and we're going to go ahead and take
this sleeve off now just simply give it
a nice little pull it's going to slide
right off for you since you already have
it in your hands you're going to want to
go ahead and wipe down your bushings
that are located on both ends of the
sleeves give it a nice little wipe down
get rid of that dust
set this guy to the side now you're
going to come over here
wipe off the end of your barbell from
all that remaining
dust gunk whatever may be in there this
is where we're getting to get that three
in one oil now so we're gonna
apply a decent amount
right where both of the bushings are
gonna be that's the only point of
contact with the sleeve and the bar
itself
go and slide our sleeve back on now
and you're going to want to go ahead and
put what was that last washer it's not
going to be your first washer
go ahead and put that on
now we're going to take our half moon
washers
and they're going to fit
nicely in this little bit of a groove
right here and when you slide the sleeve
on after this step you're going to want
to hang on to them so they don't fall on
the ground which definitely could happen
to you so let's see if we can prevent
that here
cool
now let's go ahead put that shim on if
you have one not every single barbell
has one but this one does we're gonna
put that in
followed by our next washer
now we're gonna get that inner snap ring
so
they are different so that inner snap
ring is gonna have a little bit of a
rectangle shape more so than that outer
one which is more rounded off as you can
kind of see right there
so let's go ahead and use these handy
dandy snap ring pliers here to put this
inner snap ring back into place put your
hand over top just to make sure it
doesn't fly out on you
this one might take a second it's okay
don't get frustrated like i did earlier
cool that's in there simply give your
barbell a nice little spin that's going
to go ahead and distribute that
multi-purpose oil around on those
bushings
and as you can see we've got that nice
spin that we want so let's go ahead put
our end cap back and i'll go ahead and
grab our outer snap ring just so it's
ready
put the end cap in there
once again guys don't get frustrated if
you don't get something the first time
took me quite a while the first time i
ever tried to do this so just be patient
trust me
now let's go ahead and get our outer
snap ring
make sure that's nice and tight in there
and you're good to go that's all it
really takes to clean your loading
sleeve on the barbell
so just go ahead once you're done with
that first side do the other one same
exact process actually pretty easy to
follow but could be a little difficult
along the way so once again be
patient all right now
let's talk about cleaning that knurling
so
over time like obviously your hands are
rubbing up against this knurling you're
gonna get some dead skin cells as gross
as that sounds as well as dirt dust
chalk whatever it may be it's gonna get
built up in there so this is when you're
gonna wanna go ahead and have your
trusty brush all right so i would
recommend going ahead and just giving it
a nice rub down
while it's dry just try to get some of
that loose
buildup out of there
okay so once you do that you're going to
want to go ahead
rub in your multi-purpose oil
i'd go ahead and brush that in as well
all right guys so once you get to a nice
stopping point and you're pretty
satisfied with how your knurling on your
barbell looks go ahead and set your
brush to the side you're going to want
to get your trusty rag back out just go
ahead and wipe off any excess oil that
might be on your barbell
cool all right now
there's a few ways that you can store
your barbell after you're done using it
now a lot of y'all at home may only have
one barbell and that's totally fine you
might not really need more than one
barbell so if that's the case you have a
squat rack or power rack i would
definitely suggest just storing it on
your j-hooks like we have with our bar
on our power rack over here it's gonna
hold it nice and exactly how you want it
to be no unwanted tension and weak
points now they do have
wall mounts and vertical mounts for your
barbells which one's the best so if you
do have more than one bar i would
suggest getting a wall mount to go on
your wall it's going to house your
barbells horizontally my opinion this is
ideal because it's not going to put any
unwanted force and tension in weak
points like i mentioned with the power
rack now with those vertical racks might
be
pretty easy to store it but
i don't think that's ideal especially
with a multi-purpose bar such as this
one because it's gonna put a lot of
force on these bushings and you really
don't want that it's gonna damage it and
maybe even decrease the lifespan of it
two really important things here for you
guys i would not ever recommend
storing your barbell with some weight
plates on there please don't do that
it's going to really decrease the
lifespan of your barbell and it may even
cause it to bend or warp over time and
that's obviously something that you do
not want second thing here is don't lean
your barbell up against a wall
that's not good for it like i said it's
gonna put tension on the bushings you
don't want that at all so please don't
do that okay so let's talk about the
money that you're gonna have to spend on
your supplies to make sure you take care
of your barbell the proper way all right
so you can get all this stuff at your
local hardware store we did have to run
down the lows to get this set of snap
ring pliers they were about 40 bucks but
it was worth it in the long run this 15
pair i got really did not get the job
done this was worth that extra 25 bucks
or so now some fitness companies such as
rogue actually have a barbell care kit
you can purchase that's going to include
your multi-purpose oil as well as your
brush to clean your knurling that's
going to be about 13 or so right before
shipping and handling so that's actually
a pretty good deal but if you don't want
to do that like i said you can go to
your local hardware store that's why i
got this three in one oil it's four
ounce bottle it's about four bucks
the brush is about ten dollars
my gloves i have those are also about 10
bucks as well as my safety glasses so
all in all you're looking at spending
around 70 or so it really isn't that bad
especially if you're one of those people
that's going to do this a good amount
and really going to help extend the
lifespan of your barbell all right y'all
that's all i have today on how to
properly clean and care for your barbell
this is a really simple process
especially once you get the hang of it
and you do it a couple times it's not
going to take you that long plus in my
opinion i think it's really essential
for you to do and it's going to make
sure your barbell does stay in good
condition for many years to come
thanks for watching everybody hope i
answered some questions that you might
have and showed you step by step exactly
how to take care of your barbell stay on
the lookout for more videos like this
one but in the meantime head over to
barbin.com you can read up on this
process just search barban how to clean
and care for a barbell and it's going to
pull up everything we talked about here
today i'll see you next time
[Music]